What would you say are the requirements
for somebody who tries to practice
towards right view in
the lay environment with all its
responsibilities and duties that it
comes with?
>> Uh well, first of all, try to minimize
those. Um
Um
obviously keep the precepts first of
all. Including salary receipt if you're
Including salary receipt if you're
actually serious.
Cuz um
see, you wouldn't be doing that
if you have been if you had developed
the connection
of what suffering is, what the light is,
how your own actions influence it.
Just like for as long as you keep that
there and any action that is obviously
rooted in in craving and unwholesome
states, you're maintaining your non-seeing of
you're maintaining your non-seeing of
craving as an issue.
Even if you abstractly recognize, oh
yeah, that you know, monks are
uh uh uh uh
practicing the ideal way because they're
they are giving these things up. For you
internally, this is not felt as a
problem and that's what the wrong view
is. It's not just like
It's not just like
uh theoretical, right? Cuz otherwise
anybody who just
thinks about like changes their opinions
externally can just become a sotapanna
overnight. And then the Buddha wouldn't say like
And then the Buddha wouldn't say like
how how how unique and how amazing it is
for somebody to develop the right view.
So, you basically, yeah, cut out those
you basically, yeah, cut out those
things that that are obviously against
the practice.
>> [snorts]
>> And then let's say those other
responsibilities you have that are um
left after you have cuz you you see,
many of those responsibilities and
duties and engagements are there only
because of these things that you haven't
given up.
Unnecessary things.
Uh so, once you remove those, you're
going to be left with the things that
are actually neutral.
In terms of like um um the intention
while you're doing them.
And now within that you can start to um
well, obviously there's always going to
be some level of of
um your own input. Like you can't have
the the perfect environment that
prevents you from acting out.
There's always going to be a possibility
for you to take things up wrongly even
within the precepts.
Um but then you can start to have let's
say a similar level of
uh self-questioning
as to like
it's going to have to be let's say even
more more um
made with with a with a even more sharp
level of transparency.
It as to like why am I doing these
things? And you're going to have to separate
And you're going to have to separate
that from the fact that everybody around
you is doing it cuz that has an
influence as well on your values. Like
well, it shouldn't but that's the state
you find yourself in. The fact that
pretty much everybody around you is
going the opposite direction.
And then
um
you kind of you're trying to develop the
opposite. And then
for many people that automatically
almost for everyone, that automatically
makes it unpleasant. Like just having to
go against what everybody else is doing.
That's why you have that sūtra that
describes like uh here will we we um
other people will be cruel, here we will
here we will not be cruel. Other people
will not be celibate, here we will be
celibate and so on. Describes all these
unwholesome things.
It's because
um
in order to actually start taking that
that intention as the criteria, you will
have to separate it from
this this um collective sort of
uh judgment.
And uh
that applies as a monk as well cuz you
know you could be in the in the monastic
environment take just taking for granted
that these things are good, not
clarifying why.
But in the lay life, it's it's like
it's more than just your views. It's
like you can also be tempted to act out
of stuff much more.
Uh so then
you have to um
well, keep the precepts, but then also
stick to that recognition even more to
that questioning even more
uh um aggressively, let's say.
Like when people want to talk to you,
uh let's say it's not anything
unwholesome, it's it's not anything
sexual, it's not against the precepts.
Well, but are you delighting? Like do do
you catch yourself now
um
your mind sort of like
you see that it has its own momentum
that it wants you to continue engaging
in this conversation
regardless of what the the practical
reason for it was.
And then see, all that peer pressure,
all that kind of uh
the fact that those people don't even
understand the practice that you're
doing and would completely think you're
crazy if you try to explain it, all of
that is going to pressure you even
harder. Like it's going to make it even
more difficult to say no in those
situations. But you will have to because the mind
But you will have to because the mind
that you're training is the same that
the defilements that you're abandoning
is the same, and they certainly won't go
anywhere if you're still giving in to
them. In fact, they they most certainly won't
In fact, they they most certainly won't
be weaker
when you're in an environment that
breeds them even more. So, it's it's
it's quite uh
naive to think that you can do less work
to get the same benefit,
which is what a lot of people think.
So, that's basically what it bo- boils down
that's basically what it bo- boils down
to. Like you're going to have to have
an even higher level of so-
self-transparency cuz you have all these
aids for covering things up.
>> And what about like in lay life,
you know, especially these days in the
Western world, you have a kind of life
of comfort, a lot of security, medical
care, welfare state, and so on and so
forth. Would you say that that's in and of
Would you say that that's in and of
itself an obstacle to practice as a lay
person, so that a lay person makes the
environment more difficult or more
uncomfortable? >> Yeah, well, see if if if you think that
>> Yeah, well, see if if if you think that
the comfortable circumstances
are in itself hindering you,
then you again lose sight of
what the delight is, what the craving
is, what all the defilements are. So,
let's say practically speaking, for most
people, there will be some level of
dependence and actual emotional
dependence on those things.
Uh but even that is targeted. So, it's
not that they're depending dependent on
the entire scope of uh modern comfort.
Some of them they they may not actually
care about
all that much. Even if they find them
pleasant, but again, the mind doesn't
have that kind of
uh um
compulsion and and and and
obsessive uh relationship with it.
So, if you give those things up
if you give those things up
just because they're comforts and and
you sort of think that that will develop
your mind, then that's
self-mortification. And it's certainly not developing the
And it's certainly not developing the
criteria of what craving is. So,
in a way, it's more like you should be
aware that
those things are creating the gateway
like anything else, like the comforts
that the Buddha had back in the day,
which you know, there was also
technology back then relative to
where people were before. They were
things that were being introduced that
were not there before, and they felt
like revolutionary or whatever,
and you could start becoming dependent
on those.
And and and taking safety in those.
So, it's more like you recognize that as
a as a
potential basis for delight, a potential
basis for taking safety. But, that
doesn't mean you assume that just
because it's comfortable, I'm already
finding safety in it. Therefore, if I
remove it, I'm I'm finding less safety.
So, it's like um
Yeah, think about like what what uh see
how your mind reacts to
let's say the prospect of not having
immediate access to uh medical care.
Like, it's not you're going to die or
something. It's just like
It's just like
the the the prospect of it is slightly
more distant.
Or or let's say sometimes even not even
medical care, like some some people
would even start freaking out even if
they're just because they're not able to
eat more than one meal a day.
And they know that it's not actually
going to kill them, that they're eating
enough calories, but it's still this
irrational sort of
need for something that is actually
relatively or or was relatively rare in
the past.
But again, that's not the point. The
point is
you can see the dependence that's there.
You can see the compulsion that's there.
You're not just seeing, "Oh, this is
comfortable, therefore it's bad." No,
you're seeing, "My own mind,
I can see how it feels threatened
if I if when I remove this."
It's not abstract like just just
preemptively making that judgment. You actually see
making that judgment. You actually see
the the sort of
edge that starts to build up if if these
things are even put under question
temporarily. Um So, yeah, that's what you want to
Um So, yeah, that's what you want to
start seeing. Like, you want to see the
actual obsessions that your mind has.
Cuz if you start uh dealing with
everything, um
um
even if you actually removed the things
that were an issue,
that's wrong.
Because you're again, you're not developing the
you're again, you're not developing the
criteria, and those thing those
dependencies will have moved onto
something else, but now you think you
dealt with it.
So, it's like that's that's when the
Buddha described the craving as uh
it it um
it delights here and there.
It's not like it's oh, this specific
thing that always causes craving.
You can be left without senses.
And and everything that you previously
would have depended on is gone.
And still the as long as there is any
consciousness, your mind will find
something to latch onto, and you will
think that it's not an issue.
Because you projected the problem onto
these external things.
So, in similar in the suttas, you have
all these stories of like how the the
ascetics would blame or or think that
the Buddha is not pure
because he eats all this fine food
sometimes, and and wears all these fine
robes sometimes.
Um
and actually, it's like he gave the
simile of
um
you have two people.
One of them has
the worst house, the worst food,
the worst horses, the worst everything,
but he can't give it up. He's dependent
on it.
Uh and then there's the other one who
has the best house, the best horses, the
best everything,
but he gives it up overnight.
Like his mind doesn't have this this
uh uh obsessive relationship with it.
And then that other person is the one
who actually succeeds.
So, then you could see like you could
have all the modern comforts,
everything. Again, it's not up to you, but like
Again, it's not up to you, but like
theoretically,
it's not in those things. It's in that
that obsessive relationship that your
mind has, the threat that it feels when
it's removed. So, that was the same with
the Buddha. Like he could have all these
uh comfortable things,
but literally overnight, he left the
palace and then he had to sleep next to
the side of the road.
And then he was not bothered at all.
And then see, it's not like some
ascetics would think, "Okay, so
why don't you just always sit on the
side of the road then?
Like, isn't that safer?"
And it's like, "No, because you're if
you're trying to remove things that are
not a problem as I said,
you abandon the right gateway.
You're not looking at your intentions
anymore." And then precisely those people would
And then precisely those people would
have this
uh all these defilements underlying this
external efforts to always be sleeping
on the side of the road, always be doing
What is that? Well, it's restlessness.
Like, all this greed and preferences and
dependencies externally were replaced by
this constant pressure to deny these
things. And then if those uh conditions are
And then if those uh conditions are
compromised, even accidentally,
they feel you hit with that arrow.
Because the mind was dependent on that
now. Even though it wasn't unwholesome,
it was it was just like this was the
thing that the mind latch onto now.
So then rather than trying
to
kind of do a general way of reducing the
comfort or
whatever. I mean, the eight precepts already aim
I mean, the eight precepts already aim
for most of the comfort. Well, that
removes the wrong the types of comfort
that are definitely wrong.
>> Yeah.
>> The ones that are definitely based on
delight, definitely based on obsessions.
>> So, try to establish yourself or try to
practice in the precepts as much as
possible. And then when you are kind of
confident in that, then rather than
trying to reach a certain level of
asceticism as a lay person,
aim for the more specific things.
>> Yeah.
>> That sometimes might be, sometimes might
not be.
>> And stay on that ambiguous level of like
the things that could be unwholesome.
Because even if it feels
uh riskier,
uh that's the only place that you That's
That's the only place where you can actually
the only place where you can actually
find safety.
Like initially when you're not developed in
initially when you're not developed in
that perspective, it feels like kind of
almost like unstable
to to just watch your intentions and not
be worried about what it is externally. Uh
Uh
but it's the other way around cuz any
issue could have only ever come because of
could have only ever come because of
that internal counterpart of your mind.
So then it's like it actually puts you
in danger
to be focused on the externals cuz
again, inevitably you will let things
through that should not have been let
through because you're not looking
at the right gateway.
>> So in the case of health care, if a
person finds him or herself
agitated by the thought of
visiting or moving to a country and not
having so much access to health care,
what would be the right way
to to practice with that when the mind
resists the thought of
yeah, not having easy access to health
care or no access at all.
>> Right.
Yeah, well, if you see the threat,
um
there can't That's That's the scenario
where like or you see the the how the
mind feels threatened.
That's the scenario where exposing
yourself to that discomfort could
actually bear fruit.
So like that That's the scenario where
for example in the sutras uh
uh you would do the tutanga, let's say,
because you actually feel under threat
if you don't have a roof over your head
or or if you sleep in an open space.
Um so then that creates that pressure
where you'll be able to now
you'll be able to now
let's say more easily highlight, oh this
is the problem.
This is the This is where I feel the
arrow. This is where the kind of like
This is where the kind of like
as we were saying before, the the
impulse that that underlies the unpleasant
that that underlies the unpleasant
feeling, to respond to it, to sort of do
something about it.
That's where you'll be able to to
practice that perspective in regard to
it, because as I was saying before,
that's what overcomes it. It's not like
a
you just do a series of steps 1 2 3 and
then you hope for it to go away. It's
like an- any of that that you do is just
an- any of that that you do is just
going to be aiming at the unpleasant
feeling. It's not going to be aiming at the
It's not going to be aiming at the
mind's tendency when the unpleasant
feeling arises.
So, the only way to undo that tendency
is to keep it in perspective. That's
what the Satipatthana Sutta describes.
To to capture it.
To to to um
to keep it in check.
So, that you don't give it anything to
latch onto.
To sort of
gain and and keep uh absorbing momentum.
And that's how it fades. So, like you
put yourself in the environment without
health care, for example.
Let's say ideally you should only do
that type of thing when when you already
see your mind, cuz then you you can be
confident that you will use it
rightly and won't just expose yourself
to a risk and you might die. Yeah.
Um and uh
and then you practice that perspective
when those pressures are coming up.
And then you will see, oh actually
I managed to make this subside.
The actual
obsession compulsion behind it and make
it subside while the the the perception
of the threat is completely unchanged.
So, I still know 100% that I might die
or might get sick.
It's not that I just again explained it
away and like, oh well, it's not really
an issue because blah blah blah. No, I
still recognize this would be bad and I
it would be nice to prevent it and so
on. But even if it happens, my mind will not
But even if it happens, my mind will not
be moved. In other words, there will not
be that that impulsive reaction to this
pleasure. So, um
So, um
and of course, that's that will probably
take a while.
Like it's cuz again, if you don't see
your mind,
you can sort of expose yourself to
things and then slightly cover it up and
then you overcome it for that reason,
not because you actually uh uh um
uh dealt with the root of it.
But you certainly have to
be exposed to some level of challenge of
that kind.
So, for example, if the precepts uh
don't really uh
let's say create any any sort of
internal uh uh the the doesn't doesn't
ruffle your feathers anymore,
uh then as I said, there surely has to
be something else
that you're dependent on.
So, then you go on to that to sort of
start seeing that mind more clearly,
start seeing what the problem is more
clearly. Um and
Um and
you will know when it's enough, like
when it's already kind of
it's coming up, it's challenging,
I'm sort of slightly slipping into
acting out of it,
uh but it's not so much that I would
just like just be completely overwhelmed
and quit the whole thing.
>> Yeah, it doesn't necessarily mean as
well that you straight in it where you
need to move for go visit a third world
country, but you could just deny
yourself like taking an ibuprofen
whenever you have a headache.
>> For example, yeah.
>> Or doing all kinds of random checkups
with the doctor because it could be a 1%
chance that you have
>> Yeah, or or these little efforts to like
optimize your health
that like again, are based on that
pressure, based on that compulsion.
And you
refrain from that and you just kind of
stay with the thought of, "Oh, maybe
I'll uh live 20 years less
uh live 20 years less
because I didn't do this little, I don't
know, special type of tea."
And then that brings up the the pressure
and then you will have to endure it.
>> And what about questioning the
underlying assumption of
if I only have access to the right kind
of medical care or if I get the right
checkup, if I get the right medicine,
then everything will be all right and I
can start practicing or everything is
sorted cuz there seems to be an
underlying assumption is not just like the fear of
assumption is not just like the fear of
pain
>> Mhm.
>> or displeasure, but
uh
kind of underlying assumption that is
the solution
to
my suffering.
>> Yeah, well, there is a it is the a
version to displeasure.
It just covers itself up
>> Mhm.
>> in this kind of excuse that, "Oh, yeah,
I need this because the health is so
important for the practice and so on."
Which is true.
But what practice are you doing
what practice are you doing
if [laughter] you're acting out of
craving? So, So,
um
it's like
you do need it, but
when it's uh
um tainted with that pressure
necessarily, that's not necessary. That
part is not necessary. So, So,
um
that's what you have to keep an eye on
because like as you were saying before, one day
like as you were saying before, one day
it might be like completely fine,
there's no pressure behind it, the next
day it is.
Uh so, it's not that because, again,
it's about health, it's automatically
justified or because it's about health,
it's bad because then I'm cultivating
intoxication with health automatically.
It's do I have the compulsion there? Do I
do I have the compulsion there? Do I
have the the
inability to say no to this and just
kind of
go to something else without the mind
revolving around it.